[Music]
so we're meeting for the first time in
person but we've all pretty much been on
each other's podcasts Daniel I think we
spoke about a year ago
no like six months ago six months ago
Wow
and Mike we were we were on future
thinkers or you were on yeah we did a
dual episode
yeah the dual episode three months ago
something like yeah yeah so it's really
interesting we're at the same event here
we're obviously kind of in a lot of the
same networks and we're looking we're
interviewing a lot of the same people
we've all had Jordan Greenhalgh on
Danish Max and Berger if you had Jamie
wheel won't you know it's gonna happen
yes inevitable yeah and so yeah I think
it's really interesting to talk about
kind of where we feel like we all feel
that we're part of this same
conversation looking at different parts
of it with different emphases I think we
can talk about what kind of different
embassies are but what's really
interesting is that this conversation
seems to be becoming this is dangerous
to talk about without sounding really
wanky and really kind of pretentious but
there's a sense that this conversation
is becoming a little bit more self-aware
and we've kind of trying to play with
different names for it I've heard it
called the metal web the sense making
web intellectual deep web with something
compared to kind of intellectual dark
web was something that we were playing
with for a while what's your favorite
word I actually really like the
intellectual light web because it's a
little bit if it kind of like a little
bit farcical you know and doesn't it
clearly is not taking itself too
seriously
which I appreciate but the sense making
web I think is sense making web and game
B seem to be the two frames that I see
having the most momentum at least like
in my neck of the woods yeah for me it's
the minimum viable meme is what I'm
looking for so I actually really agree
with you on game B I think that works
yeah and how would you summarize the
differences in terms of like your
particular focus and your particular
focus on future thinkers we have less of
a structure than I think you guys do
which we kind of
wherever we feel like going historically
speaking that's been the case now we are
definitely focusing a lot more on sense
making and sovereignty as far as Daniel
smarty burgers defined it that's become
a huge thing I always wanted to focus on
big problems in the world and how do we
actually start to approach those and you
and I have both continually landed on
the conclusion that it becomes it more
important to focus on individual
sovereignty and how we make sense of the
world that's where everything starts
yeah I suppose like you know in my mind
I think there are obviously an avid
listener to oh I wasn't mean both of
your projects I don't really listen to
my own you know but any so the
distinction that I feel for me is
something about the exploration one I
feel like my podcast is a bit more like
kind of philosophical and sort of like
performative like there's a kind of
aesthetic to it that isn't quite like an
interview it's more like a dance like a
conversational dance like for me I was
very inspired by like authentic relating
and sort of just the possibility of
having a beautiful conversation where
something new is discovered in the
meeting of the conversation right and
then definitely takes place I know in
both of your projects but for me that's
more of a kind of aesthetic like that's
been guiding me the whole way and yeah
again like the kind of playing more in
this philosophical conceptual territory
I think it feels like it's very much a
part of my project yeah yeah and I'm
interested I mean we've we're all kind
of talking about practice now it's like
there's a real focus on practice and how
to get ourselves into these spaces for
generative dialogue and sovereignty
that's a real focus for all of us but I
think definitely I feel that with with
you Daniel because I'm fascinated by
your kind of a modern monk hermit living
in a monastery putting these kind of
what Peter Lindbergh will call mimetic
artifacts out into the world that must
be a really interesting
to be part of well yeah definitely mean
it it it is also the case that it was
through the exploration of the podcast
that I it was revealed to me that I
actually had to go into training to
embody this sort of world that was being
called for I think in the conversations
were having like it was revealed to me
how important personal transformation
was like not that I was like not doing
work on myself but just how core that
was and how to some degree I was like
fooling myself thinking that I was more
in integrity with what that was asking
then I was you know and so that's part
of the reason I went back and yeah like
I don't know that I would be able to
have the conversations I'm having
without like participating in this kind
of space of practice you know for me to
do it because a lot of these things can
get so abstract
you're not like living it - it's I don't
feel like it would work or make sense
yeah and I want to want to back up a
little bit and just for people maybe who
are watching you not sort of familiar by
where we're taking a lot for granted
here in terms of even talking about
practice and talking about sovereignty
and like for me what I found very really
useful was I did a training as a
counselor and so I've got a background
as a journalist but I also did training
as a counselor about a year and a half
two years ago and I really felt a
different quality of my interviews from
that space when I was able to be much
more present and much more available and
that I think has really informed a lot
of the the interviews that that I've
done since on um rebel wisdom and it's
it's much more about about how present
can you be and how present in the moment
can you be in there's all sorts of
different practices that can help with
that from now mindfulness to circling
authentic relating all that sort of
stuff and what would you say might
what's your kind of relationship to to
practice and have you felt things
shifting you know you've kind of put it
in perspective for me a little bit -
just describing your your path through
this the conversation that we have on
future thinkers is really a couple's
conversation and it started off just
this breakfast-time conversation and has
gone through so we've had this these
sort of
contemplative practices and
conversations about psychology and and
developmental psychology and society and
these things just became something we
thought maybe other people would be
interested in so we turned on the
recorder so the conversation that we
have with other people as well as kind
of the same it's like they're entering
into our conversation that's continually
evolving the practice itself has just
been part of our lives just it wasn't
something worth talking about for us
until the podcast turned on but deep
meditation we focused a lot in our
meditation practice on resilience and
focusing on dealing with and processing
difficult emotions and in doing that for
a long enough time it became really
difficult to find more things to become
emotional over or Reaction reactive to
and that was interesting so we just
started talking about that yeah just to
say it's a real shine UV can't be with
us well it's because she's seven months
pregnant now so she can't move so we're
gonna have our own little psychology
experiment in a few months
yeah that would be a learning experience
yeah yeah and and also I just want to
what's really interesting to me as well
is that the I don't know if it's partly
just the sort of the personal biases
that I'm personally bringing into it and
maybe we're all bringing to it but this
sense of a lot of things moving in the
same direction that this sort of
personal practice world has been coming
together more with the systems change
and the existential risk and all these
bigger topics but it feels like there's
a really fascinating teleology direction
to this conversation I think we're all
feeling and I wonder whether that's our
personal bias that we're projecting into
it or whether it is and it is something
that's emerging from the conversation I
have something to say about that I think
is really has been really interesting to
watch because I think I've got my pot
guest has been around for quite a while
compared to you guys and it's just been
this conversation that's just been
really whatever if we feel like that
month it's never had a direction or a
line but other people have pointed out
to us that over time years of doing this
there is a line to it it's that there is
a narrative that has emerged and so that
with this movement there's a lot of
focus on
how do we direct it how do we become
conscious and direct it and I feel like
the whole idea of emergence and
collective sense making is that it comes
along without your focus and attention
it just emerges out of its own
properties and I think the attempt to
kind of focus and direct it is actually
almost working against the movement yeah
I mean so what's coming up for me is
it's like you know there's a way in
which we are actually we are
participating in the like the creation
of a new meta-narrative right and we're
kind of like as we're participating the
creation of it we're also being
subjected to it right and there's this
kind of feedback loop where it starts to
gain some momentum of its own and then
it's kind of like wait are we biasing it
or we observing it what is happening
here and I think we're actually had a
really interesting inflection point
where as you're saying like it feels
like there's something happening here
like are we doing it and it actually is
a lot like some spaces in meditation
right where you're like am I making this
happen am i am i doing this or is this
like actually happening what what you
know and I think that actually that is
just how it is right like that's how
it's going to go down is we're gonna
like participate this into being it's
like not gonna be real or not real but
it's gonna like have an impact
it's getting new stuff and it's like an
important and significant yeah yeah I
think they line through it all will
emerge and a lot more clarity as more
people or participate in the
conversation yeah yeah yeah the piece
around like there's this kind of feeling
of like harmony or integrity of the
personal work and the kind of mmm like
vision of the future of systems in
general of like this kind of like idea
of Omni win right
it's like Omni win planet yes Omni win
nation yes Omni win community yes Omni
win like in this triad yes
Omni win in my psyche right like there
are parts of me can I bring them into
harmony so they're all kind of like
playing a game well together I was like
I think that the to the degree that we
can see that harmony conceptually and
live it like
like hell yes right and I I don't know
that that was in the mimetic space like
very long though it certainly wasn't in
my mimetic space and like I was deep in
I was a deep nerd about this stuff and
like this feels new to me yeah yeah I
feel like there's so many different
branching points here one of which is
the nature of the online space does seem
to create these positive feedback loops
like that there's not a scarcity like
that for example
people can watch or listen to all of our
podcasts and the fact that we are
talking to each other is not there's
there's no scarcity here it's not like
if they're not watching my channel
they're watching your channel and we're
in rivalry with each other whereas where
I come from Channel 4 News in the BBC
and you're not promoting each other's
channels you don't promote each other
channels because if someone's watching
BBC News they're not watching Channel 4
News or whatever that there's an
implicit so there is already in the
digital world the possibility for
non-rivalry Stein Amex in a way that I
don't think there were before
I mean if tension is finite on some
level so it doesn't go all the way down
but but certainly and there are many
more positive feedback loops and the new
digital media environment there were in
the old media environment the other the
other branch that I was feeling as well
was this sort of only win dynamic you're
talking about in game B the idea of game
B is the sort of none rival or a space
and I had a real realization on our most
recent workshop men's retreat where I
was like oh actually this space that
we're creating is is a game B space like
I'm sure you've had the experience as
well on a workshop of just this space
that opens up on say day 3 day 2 or day
3 where you can just feel the field
change and there's a lot more
authenticity and there's this sort of
sense of another a third or another
space opening up where the air becomes
sort of heavy with significance and
there's there's no real way language for
explaining this kind of stuff that
doesn't feel cliched or weird
but I realized in the closing circles I
okay this is this is game B this is what
we've been making all these films about
because there is something that we're
craving on such a deep level where we're
in our space where everyone wants the
best for each other and when someone
really kind of has a realization or
shows up in a new way they're honored
for that and it's like wow yes I someone
shares something really vulnerable or
has some kind of insight and everyone is
there with them and wanting the best for
them and it's like we've lost so much of
that because we're caught in these
zero-sum games with each other and
defensiveness patterns and all of this
and so yeah that's too kind of possible
branches for the conversation I don't
man yeah which one you want to jump on
yeah I've been trying to figure out what
it is at the heart that that changes in
that group dynamic you know from there's
not a flow state there's what what you
described there to suddenly we're all in
harmony with each other and I'm trying
to isolate that point and get down to
the bottom of it and I think it has
something to do with our desire to be
perceived a certain way and project are
our best image to each other and in
doing so we're less focused on the truth
of what's happening in the conversation
and more on how we're being perceived
and and so I put a lot of focused into
that and with what we are talking about
in the podcast now and in our courses
that has become just such a central
point and in focusing on that I've
noticed an unlocking and sense-making
immediately and an unlocking and
collective intelligence that is just I I
haven't been able to experience anywhere
else and with any other groups in such a
stable way as what we've been able to do
with our our weekly calls the course
calls and it's just it's so simple but
it's so hard to to get through to that
point where you can actually just listen
and look for truth in a group
conversation yeah and I think it's
really significant that and I have a
similar sense of what is happening in
the in the monastery and the community
that I did I live at that there's a way
in which and I think it actually has
always been the case that monasteries
have been these kind of omni when local
systems right
and that there's the most important
teaching there is actually what it's
like just to be in that space right and
if you do workshops if you've done
retreats you get to this point you're
like oh this is so wonderful this is and
then you say but I have to go back to
the real world right and it's like is
there is what we're talking about to
some degree like taking the real world
and making it more like these like
beautiful spaces that we sometimes get
to participate because we're very
privileged and it's like maybe that
sounds amazing that sounds really great
and I think it's cool that we all have
like different ways that we're offering
these kinds of experiences like you know
whether it's online or residential or a
weekend retreat you know and that you
can get this like taste because I think
that that's there is the the
conversational aspect the cognitive
aspect but then there's the the the
taste the flavor of it that I think is
perhaps more important yeah actually
probably more important
yeah I've always found those sort of
peak State experiences and there's other
ways of getting there as well as sort of
plant medicines and those Peak State
experiences like there's really extreme
ones as well I think almost feel like I
said a calling card and one of the most
fascinating conversation I had around
that was with Jordan Pederson just
before the cameras were rolling and so I
went over it - yeah so - two years ago
when I did the interview with Jordan
Peterson I'd gone to his lecture the
night before and he talked about Young's
idea of the self with the capital S as
something that is calling to us from the
future that this sort of potential that
the potentially about potentiality of
our personality calling to us from the
future through our interests through the
things that we are drawn to do in our
lives there's some sort of relationship
with this sort of kind of I don't know
feels a bit my terence mckenna's kind of
object at the end of time almost but and
I feel that that made so much sense I
just had this kind of like realization I
talked to him just before the cameras
are rolling about how meaningful I found
that because it felt like my
Peak State experiences were like been in
a in a completely open flow state and
they've lasted like a couple of weeks at
a time for months at a time I'm just
like I don't need to think I just act
from this real deeper space in myself
those peak experiences like almost like
calling to me from in some way they have
this deeper resonance that feels like
it's it's something in the future that's
calling and orienting myself towards in
an almost like gravitational field kind
of way yeah yeah even her people at this
gathering refer to like attractors right
which is a similar kind of sentiment I
think more in terms of like systems
theory where you have like the
possibility of like an attractor in one
teacher that I really appreciate talks
about like the angel out ahead right
there kind of like tracking something
that you may never actually reach but
it's kind of like calling you forward in
a way that it perhaps actually that the
the desire to define it too rigidly
conceptually might actually kill it
right so that's kind of why the flavor
actually might be more important than
the conversation around it but I feel
that way well it's not like for me it's
not just peak experiences that's why I
think the community I live in for me is
very significant is that it's not
pleasant to be there all the time
sometimes it's actually quite horrible
right but it's within the context of a
system that you can trust right you know
that people are there for their their
benefit and your benefit and like
everything is kind of like chill like in
trustworthy and wholesome and good
fundamentally and that's there's just a
different way of being that that enables
that you don't actually see how
up this world is until you've been in
that and again it's like please do not
imagine that being in a monastery is
just one peak experience after another
it is not that definitively related your
point about the gravity well and the the
future attractor future version of
yourself there's an interview that I did
with
Kirby surprised who wrote this book
about synchronicity and he talked about
synchronicities you know those those
experiences we have of calling someone
on the phone and they're thinking of
calling us on the phone we just connect
or you know in this field that seems
like there's a lot of discussion about
synchronicity and synchronistic events
what you get what you focus on that's
what you get in this book he talked
about how synchronicity can work
forwards and backwards in time like
there can be a future event that's
pulling you towards it like one of the
examples he uses is actually an argument
with his wife this big blowup argument
that was rippling backwards and caught
he was noticing all these
synchronicities leading up to this event
of like heightened emotional frustration
and and it all just led up to this point
this is all metaphysical and unprovable
but just thinking about what we would do
if we were gonna design our experience
outside of time if consciousness can
exist outside of time how would we do it
and I would picture it being like the
design would be something like these
gravity wells experience that just pull
us through in time and it kind of lined
up with this book yeah what's coming up
for me too is that it's you know it's
these ideas don't even have to
necessarily be so metaphysical right
like the idea that time is like linear
in the past is back there and the
present is where we are now in the
future is coming like we are I think
part of what we are all sensing is that
like we are in a time of deconstruction
and B construction is happening both in
like the political economic social world
but I think it also there is an
invitation for it to happen within the
kind of world of our metaphysics and
assumptions about how reality kind of
functions and I like it for the question
for me is like are we free to play with
the idea that perhaps time flows
differently than we've been taught right
not like to make a grand claim about the
nature of reality but just to see what
that opens up in terms of a space of
experimentation that might allow us to
kind of like I don't know do something
different because what's work what we've
been doing is not going to get us to
where we need to go and so it's like
yeah like those
kinds of sort of like flips I think are
so significant and it but then if like
you're listening and you're like that's
not how time works it's like hmm okay so
it sounds like you're not free to play
in that way yeah no yeah it's
interesting the discussion about these
kind of metaphysical things always have
to come with this disclaimer like it's
not proven I don't I don't really mean
what I'm saying but it's really just an
experiment in a conversation see where
we can take it and what lens do you look
through that gives you a completely
different perspective in the world and
maybe makes other things make sense like
this whole idea of synchronicity and
time being only something we experience
in a linear fashion but maybe it's all
existing at the same time that allows
you you know more lenses to view things
through which is something that reminds
me of John Vevey keys work in particular
because he it's really interesting to
see the development of consciousness and
the development of the idea of even
linear time this sort of Western
narrative over of a beginning a middle
and an end and time as a kind of arrow
moving in one direction is actually it
actually had a beginning like it's not
just the way understanding how much of
our cognitive framework has actually is
not pre stuff we just assume as
pre-given has actually arrived at
certain moments in the past and we were
in more of an eternal now before then
and maybe we're in one of those big
shifts where we're becoming aware by
becoming aware of how our thought has
been patterned gives us a chance to
actually maybe reflect on a lot of the
what we assumed was pre given
cognitively and there's also another
link that just came up with the internet
I think Jordan Hall has talked about it
as being eternal memory so we're now in
a from the idea of kind of synchronous
broadcast media we're now in a world of
eternal memory and kind of an eternal
now in some senses yeah yeah Douglas
rushkoff
writes about this in his book present
shock and it which is really striking
for me it's like there's it's like we're
in an eternal presence but it's like a
very mmm like not the kind of eternal
presence that you know you want to be
and it's an eternal presence of
distraction and like confrontation
from your devices and from like the
world coming and invading your space
right and it's yes there is a really
funny way in which we are forced into an
eternal presence like we've lost that
sense of historicity against our will
yeah yeah yeah yeah we're strapped in
front of the fire hose yeah you have to
stay there yeah yeah yeah actually that
was a I think the last question I asked
John for Vicki when he was on my show
was like she's talking about psycho
technologies and stuff and I was like so
like is time itself a psycho technology
and he made a very kind of interesting
distinction right this is like I'm not
saying that time doesn't exist but like
the the relationship of the human mind
the capacity to kind of participate in
time in a particular way is yes a psycho
technology that kind of like arose in a
particular time in context that's like
damn like what else are we taking for
granted there's this wonderful I haven't
read it but you know the origin of
consciousness and the bicameral mind but
stop me if I'm giving this wrong but
what I understand from that is is that
they the the the hypothesis in that is
that when for example the Greek myths
were being written they had a completely
different relationship to these
archetypes these archetypes were
actually almost like physical presences
in their lives and there wasn't this so
it's a really interesting frame to look
back at like the way that we're at the
way that we're criticizing our
understanding and mythological history
or our kind of mythopoetic history has
to be fundamentally reevaluated because
we're taking for granted a lot of things
that the consciousness itself has
fundamentally changed through through
history and our relationships to these
like the idea being that we actually did
live in a world of gods and live in a
world of spirits before and we were
actually able to kind of perceive things
in that way familiar with that yeah yeah
a little bit yeah and my sense is that
we almost like is john rebecca would say
sort of like discovered the kind of
psycho technologies that enabled us to
become rational and perceive ourselves
as like in
visuals acting in coherent ways with
each other instead of like just sort of
like being told what to do by Damon's
right and like that this might have been
like a transition point perhaps that was
the axial revolution maybe but like just
that that too is something that we can't
take for granted that that's like an
affordance of the context and evolution
of human consciousness is like you know
I think it just speaks to how deep the
deconstruction rabbit-hole can go and to
how much is like up for grabs in terms
of how much we could reimagine the human
into the future yeah I'm really curious
what some of the breaking points were in
these transitionary phases because I
feel like one of the ones that we're
having now is this transition from pure
rationality and to maybe there's more to
experiment with and think about and
which is why I focus on these kind of
frame breaking subjects like what is
time and is there such thing as all-time
existing at the same time what is
synchronicity you know and a lot of that
for me can kind of stem out of
contemplating the double-slit experiment
in quantum physics it's like the
observer effects what is being observed
and literally proven right in front of
you anyone can see that so these I get
the sense in a lot of conversation with
people that breaking out of that
rational framework is what's happening
but also you need it's almost like you
need a rational explanation of why you
need to rationally break out of the
rational framework yeah yeah I mean I
think that's what I've discovered as
being like the key entrance point is
what I've been sharing in the context of
the monastery Levin is like moving from
the sense that perception in the world
is something that you are merely
observing to realizing that it is
something that you are participating in
and it is also participating in you and
that that's a kind of like fundamental
shift they can take us out of this sense
of like things are just happening to us
and we're like watching it or consuming
it you know and like that seems to be
one of the core logics that needs to be
disrupted I think you're yeah absolutely
it's like that shift there's two things
that come up one is another reference
for another big book that I have
red but I'm fascinated the jean gebser
talked about the breakdown of the mental
rational consciousness and also a friend
of mine
Jules Evans put out a newsletter quite
recently saying entitled dude where's my
paradigm shift looking at how it's
brilliant just saying we've been talking
about the idea of an imminent paradigm
shift has been present for a long time
like certainly since the sixties and
then you look back it's actually way
before then
and this sort of sense of ok one
consciousness structure the mental
rationale is breaking down another one
is is taking its place and I've been
like I remember reading Richard Tarr
NASA's passion of the Western mind which
I still think is one of the best
analyses about current psycho
philosophical situation and where we
might be going next I think it's
fantastic and I think he's brilliant and
but yeah dude where's where's the
paradigm shift do we always think that
we're kind of on the verge of it and and
is this a tendency like is this a
tendency that we're all going to be
subject to and how do we know because we
all feel like something's happening to
quote Dave Rubin yeah what do you reckon
yeah it was what's coming up for me and
this is something that was talking about
with somebody earlier today here is that
many of the things that I think have
claimed themselves to be paradigm shifts
are in fact simply like perhaps the last
gasp of the mental rationale the mental
rationale faculty attempting to push
itself beyond what its limits are right
so like integral for instance like for
me it's like it's like the mental
rational mind trying to go beyond itself
but really it's just creating like more
more complexity more mental rational
accoutrements and descriptions of
exactly that thing which perhaps created
the context in which we find ourselves
that needs to be moved beyond and so
it's like there is a way in which all of
these kind of meta theoretic
moves aren't the thing there's something
else that is coming online that I think
is for me is this more like
participatory embodied recognition of a
difference in the nature of the human
being and they kind of like living
forward of that and so yeah that's what
came to mind yeah that's really well
said and and I think in looking at like
where's dude where's my paradigm shift
it's tempting to just look at that from
this holistic like wins everything going
to change but I think it's been this
little pop Corning of the breakdown of
rational thinking in the exploration of
other possibilities that's been
happening for the past 60 years or
whatever and it just seems like it's
nothing's changing but we can't look
forward in time and define what it is
that we're becoming but you can
definitely tell by looking back that
this is different you know yeah I I like
that I really like that reference to
integral like the sense of and I think
this is a real issue in this sort of
broader space and there's people sort of
talking about meta modernism and
integral obviously has a place within it
is the danger of just further
intellectualizing a process that is
actually the end of intellectualizing
and I think the right the rational mind
has to be integrated like that there's
also in in the more sort of spiritual
space there's a real denigration of the
intellectual as well which is which is
another dead end and I've had these sort
of conversations or it's like well just
stop thinking about it and just just
just be present with your body and
that's sort of the New Age spiritual
bypass like there is a yes and move but
what I definitely see in these circles
happening again and again and again is
just more sophisticated intellectual
ways of kind of the mind trying to free
itself from itself and it's just weaving
ever deeper webs of abstraction and and
word salad nonsense yeah it's a
fascinating dynamic which is I guess
bring us back to the point we made at
the beginning about practice
practice being primary and the embodied
being primary I find what the the kind
of conversations I have with people if
we're gonna use the integral model at
Green level criticizing past levels and
saying stop thinking with the ration or
stop thinking
don't use the rational framework so much
that type of speech is never going to
work for someone who's hyper-rational
but there are kind of codes or like kind
of instigating thought forms that can
bring a rational person out of the
rational way of thinking that are
completely rationally based I had a
conversation with someone yesterday
about this you know we were talking
about synchronicity he's like you know
I'm a physicist there's no basis for any
of this stuff and then I was like well
you're basing everything off of a
handful of miracles at the beginning of
time and then everything is just locked
into materialism from there
it's like but we all have to agree that
we don't know for sure anything and we
have to have the mental agility to be
able to experiment with new ideas and if
you're locked in this rational framework
you're not even going to bother
exploring these other ideas so you know
bringing up the double-slit experiment
or you know just daily experience of the
unexplainable synchronicity being the
example it's like these are little
things that can break people out of that
rational framework that maybe they can
start to just question but rationality
and that orange level thinking has a
tendency of confining people's thinking
yeah I find it peculiar the physicist
because physics has turned into sort of
one of the most bizarre almost spiritual
like so many of the of the great
physicists were were fascinated by
Eastern mysticism by the fact that one
thing can be two things at the same time
and this sense of physics as I kind of
my narrative of it in the 20s was that
it kind of was like we're going to
identify the fundamental building block
of reality oh no it's looking back at us
and that almost like pulling the pulling
the rug under a certainty that then kind
of framed like the twenty was amazed
amazed entire yet psychoanalysis
starting he had incredible realizations
in physics and it was it would when the
sort of the rug was being pulled and
pulled from underneath the kind of
mental rational atomistic framework and
so I find it bizarre that a physicist
would say would kind of how physicists
could still be a kind of arch
materialist well you know he's that he
was a physicist who was also a
rationalist and you can you can be one
of the other you don't have to be both
and embedded in like our current culture
and like raised up in our public
education or education systems and
subject to our economy you know all of
it is kind of like to some degree
participating in the reification of that
kind of paradigm and so it's like yeah
you know maybe one one stream is kind of
sort of problematizing it but it's a lot
of work I think we it's hard to
overestimate to the degree to which the
mental rationale will kind of like hold
on to its paradigm and it's hard to like
it it's easy I think to because we can
talk about it it's hard it's actually
incredibly hard to move beyond it even
for like brief periods of time and it's
like oh yeah one thing I notice about
people who are stuck in that
materialistic rational perspective is
they they have this desire for certainty
for kind of a binary answer right but
they they tend to talk about it as if
that's coming from their framework
instead of which I'm observing to be
more of an emotional response to
uncertainty not knowing the way things
are we have this desire because it gives
us a feeling of safety to know something
is a certain way and then you know
rational rationalist or whatever you
want to call them tend to use the
rational framework as a crutch
like it must be proven for me to even
experiment with the idea and that's
completely limiting yeah that's a dead
end too
wandering in maybe going into a little
bit of a sort of what's the experience
been for us in terms of kind of I love
again referring to Peter Lindbergh's
idea of kind of memetic artifacts
there's this sort of sense of where he
had was he said something like we're all
sending out mimetic artifacts into the
void and seeing what comes back and
there has been a real sense of a lot of
interest in the stuff that we're
bringing out we're putting out and I
know I'm sure you have the same thing a
lot of people getting in touch and a lot
of people following this sort of same
thread of the emerging conversation I
mean how how has that been for for you
guys I mean especially for Daniel being
in a monastery and then also being
putting all of this sort of content out
and the paradox of being kind of in the
monastery but also now in in this kind
of interconnected world being available
for anyone to kind of get in contact
it's partially available I've actually
like sort of like not intentionally like
there's no comments you can make on my
podcast
you know I'm not on YouTube I don't have
a website really I'm part of this larger
brand is actually kind of hard to get in
touch with me we're gonna put Daniels
email address oh that's great right now
but but nonetheless people do and it's
actually hard because I feel like I want
to like give more to them but I live in
a monastery I live in a monastery and
like you know I have my time is all very
spoken for but the sense that I get and
I imagine this is true for all of us is
that we're like we are putting out a
signal that is creating some kind of
resonant field that people are like
feeling drawn into that they want to
participate in that they want more from
like there's some pathos there like they
want there to be more and it's amazing
it's humbling for me that's super cool
to be a part of like I feel really lucky
being that we're out in Bulgaria I feel
it's like self-exiled probably feel some
of the similar similar situation for you
and it's some it often feels like you're
just shouting out into the darkness
shouting these ideas out and then maybe
people are hearing them maybe they're
not but the fact that you know what I
said earlier but that having all of
these different subjects and talking
about whatever you feel whatever feels
like is emerging and interesting it's
just fascinating to me how people are
picking up on a narrative that was never
intended and that's the same thing I
think that we're talking about here
there is some sort of narrative that's
just happening while all of these things
are seeming to simultaneously bubbling
up around us the one thread I'd love to
pick up from from our conversation
before which is integration because we
mentioned peak experiences and I think
those are incredibly valuable but I also
think that what a lot like my personal
journey has been very much and I find it
quite easy to have those peak
experiences and my personal journey of
kind of integrating that into my life
has been a long a long one I think
that's really valuable to talk about
like what is the what are the sort of
hard yards of integration of these kind
of peak ego dissolving experiences in a
hard hard hard yards hard yards yeah so
this position was I mean that's an
American thing never know yeah it's not
a Canadian thing the difficult work oh I
think okay hard yards I I'm sure that's
American it's not the sort of thing I'd
say yeah and just I mean one one thread
is well I became a kind of workshop
junkie I did I did sort of a lot of
plant medicines psychedelics at
university had huge openings there that
I actually found quite difficult to
integrate and went through a kind of
real dark night of the soul experience
afterwards and sense of that the phrase
I came up with was living in the shadow
of myself because I had this sort of
taste of have really been
really tapping into a bigger version of
myself and then that was unsustainable
through through the psychedelics and I
was sort of chasing that thing for a
while and the gap between that and my
myself was kind of opening up and then
when I found the more personal growth
oriented work I I found I was able to
access some of the same experience but
it was much more into I found it more
easy to integrate but it but I don't
think I really was able to integrate it
until I had more of those relationships
in my life like I was playing with being
more honest or being more yeah playing
with with greater depth and greater
honesty in the workshop space but it
wasn't until I'd say that more of my
relationships in my outside and the
outside world had that quality of
presence and honesty and deeper
connection that I felt more integrated
and this sort of I think part of that is
also the the illusion of isolation or
individuality it's actually we're
actually highly networked and it's it's
through the quality of those connections
and quality of those interactions that
can we change those through like
authentic relating or circling or any of
those more deeper present practices
that's what really I think make a
sustainable change it's not the
individual peak State experiences that
when we're like okay now I'm going to
change everything in my life and
everything's gonna be different but then
kind of we come down over the course for
a month or two yeah yeah yeah I mean if
there's that saying I think like Tim
Ferriss says it's a lot but it's like
you are the average of the five people
you spend the most time with usually
it's used in the context of like
entrepreneurship and like being
materially successful but like yeah
right like it's there's a very kind of
we are
I think people in general are virulent
in a lot of ways that we don't really
recognize and to find yourself in a
commune like that's part of the reason
I'm in a monastery is like everybody's
just like completely dedicating
themselves to growth and so I think
that's a huge transition point when your
social network starts to shift and you
find yourself in in relationship with
people who are like up to the same game
and they're not like isolated anymore
you know my sense
in terms of like the hard part yards of
this kind of thing is that it's
different for every person and I think
it's like what you say at the beginning
that it's about following your like
interest your curiosity is pulling you
like I started with like you know
intensive meditation retreats other
people I know started with like
therapeutic kind of more trauma healing
and then later came to meditation other
people I know started with psychedelics
right but like there's a way in which if
you keep going it will just like it will
it will touch every arena of your life
and like letting that go down right like
letting it just consume everything over
time and not like being like oh this is
just like just meditation right just
authentic relating like allow it to keep
growing and consuming you and that's
probably like pretty it's gonna do what
it does you know like it worked its way
yeah you know it's it's funny I agree
with you that there is a some place that
you kind of arrived at but you can go to
go to it from different areas and for me
it's like I've had rope tied around my
legs and been thrown off the back of a
car and dragged through all of it the
whole way and and not so I don't really
see it throughout their lenses of like
intentional practice or you know a lot
of it was just like no you're doing this
life is dragging you through this but
there was an interview that I watched
with Jordan Peterson where he described
his own kind of awakening experience and
it had to do with with recognizing that
voice outside of his his own narrating
voice that looked at him speaking and
said that's not true that's
you don't mean that and I when I heard
him say that I really resonated with
that it was something that I went
through a very distinct period of of
like recognizing how much was
just coming out of my face and
recognizing the narrator and recognizing
that there's a there's a whole other
part of me that is criticizing and so I
really made a practice out of just
figuring out what that voice was and and
that really was a transition point for
me like everything cascaded out of that
and I I stopped getting dragged through
the mud after that point you know like
in it relates to that attractor thing I
think life just gives you the
circumstances you need to learn to be
able to to grow as a person some people
need a lot of suffering and and that's
my case but as soon as I gained
sovereignty in my own personal growth I
stopped suffering which is amazing yeah
yeah well one thing that's coming up too
is I think we talked about this a little
bit yesterday is one kind of mmm what is
this like place or pull you must pass on
this I think is whether or not you've
been thoroughly humiliated right like
and I I mean like intellectually
emotionally like that your whole being
has just been humiliated I think that
for me is actual indicator of like okay
like this person is trustworthy because
otherwise they're wrong they think that
they you need to have been broken by
life in some way yeah yeah yeah and like
this constantly trying to break you and
it's like let it yeah that's such a good
point I mean have you read that book the
surrender experiment yeah you know I
don't want to do that just do any talk
about what's what so it was a guy
Michael
a singer who wanted to just be a monk
basically he wanted to disappear away
from the world not have to deal with the
world and just focus on you know self
transcendence and and and that kind of
thing and there are so many things
around him constantly demanding his
attention you know he was teaching in a
university and he wanted to stop doing
all of that buy a plot of land out in
the middle of nowhere and just go there
and I I also recognize myself in that
too because I just went what's the
farthest place in the world I could go
to well Gary up sure let's go there and
I never came out but one thing he did
that was really inspiring to me is he
said yes to so many things is like that
yes man movie with Jim Carrey like he
just kept saying yes and he went through
just an amazing set of experiences I can
actually quite recall all of them aside
from one where he became the CEO of a
large software company somehow but maybe
you remember some of the other stories I
just kind of remember that yeah
a sense of he's just like like humbling
himself in into life like just allowing
life to tell him what to do you know
which is I think a little bit yeah like
what I'm referring to that there is like
like yeah that's there's a humility that
requires I think a degree of humiliation
typically given how we are typically
educated in our world to allow that to
happen to you yeah I think you're the
the degree to which you are stubborn is
the degree to which life will bash it
over your head and and you know I was
stubbornly rational which is why I also
realized that any other talk but
rational talk is not going to convince
someone to transcend that but I was very
stubborn so life kept hitting me with
that yeah I think it like you say like
it at the dark night like the dark for
in a lot of cases maybe not all cases
like the the length of the time you
spend in the dark night is the length of
time you are unwilling to just humble
yourself and let go right like when I
first got to the monastery some years
ago like that was basically what the the
teacher there just was like making me do
he's just like no like you don't get to
pretend you don't get to act as if you
know here maybe a day in day out
eventually you know I just it's like
fine
I get I'm really curious about that your
experience there at the monastery cuz my
experience has always been you know
disappear and I do think a lot of at
least the stories I'm interested in
which is maybe part of my lens there's
this period with big transformation
there's this period of time of deep
isolation and even exile from society
and and reflection and contemplation
it's the whole like Moses in the burning
bush that whole kind of archetypal story
is to me at the heart of a lot of
transformational stories so to have it
be in a community setting is really
foreign in really fascinating to me yeah
yeah I mean I certainly think it's the
case that like metaphorically that
happens
certainly on retreat right like you're
all there together you're in the same
space but you're completely alone
right you're just in silence sitting 12
hours a day or whatever and you know
there is a kind of existential
loneliness that you certainly become
extremely aware of in that setting and I
think in general in the monastic
container like you you're aware of how
alone you are in this journey and so
there's a way in which that happens but
you're certainly not like yeah you are
surrounded by community for sure
interesting I wouldn't have guessed that
that the experience would still be have
that loneliness component to it yeah mmm
I think there's a there's a phrase that
we came up with on our workshops we have
to do it ourselves but we don't have to
do it alone but there is a sort of
support I imagine at the at the
monastery at least that that you're
you're with people who are on a similar
journey rather than you can't talk to
about it yeah it means there's like a
growing opening to our existential
aloneness in at the same time a
deepening experience of belonging and
like community and mutuality and support
and so those in the monastic tradition
as I understand it like those two things
together are part of that kind of psycho
technology or whatever is it those two
come together because one without the
other can create a lot of danger right
well either like just hope like group
mind or you know people who do go out on
their own can
yes break through have breakthroughs but
can also lose track of like ethics and
behavior and how to behave in a way that
respects the community I think the speed
of awakening also seems to be quite
affected by how surrounded by other
practitioners you are I noticed I mean
at this event there's been a lot of
conversation about isolation and finding
the others and you know where where are
people and and I was in that bubble for
the longest time which is partially why
we started the podcast is just put up a
flag and see who comes and in doing that
and then starting meetups which you know
you guys understand this you recognize
that there's a hunger for this kind of
content and conversation and camaraderie
that you know to me the realization came
so
late and I think for a lot about other
people it hasn't come yet they just
think they're alone in this stuff and
they're really not it's really we're not
all so special you know our experience
is that whole thing like you're special
you can do anything you want I actually
think works against us we're so much
more like with each other than me than
we think and in recognizing that you
there's instant community you know the
exceptionalism is a real prison of
isolation yeah yeah you're touching on
two really interesting subjects that one
is community which is something I feel
certainly we're now focusing more and
more on how do we build community and
also the sort of difference both of you
are kind of in self-imposed isolation in
a way and we're based in the middle of
London one of the the kind of biggest
cities and it's a really interesting
like I I feel there's part of me that
would that would love to be kind of
living somewhere in the country
countryside and part of me that feels
like that's just impossible that the it
I feel like really a real need to be in
what I feel to be one of the centres of
things and I mean the UK is incredibly
kind of centralized country that
everything is focused on London the
media industry is focused on Londa
politics like everything exists in
London ice is really centralized place
and like I love the sound of the
monastery for example I couldn't I
couldn't imagine living there I think I
couldn't imagine taking that time out
like I feel the sense of urgency of
needing to be in a kind of Center - yeah
well we talked about I think a little
bit about this yesterday right I think
there's um as we encounter each other's
work there's a way in which I think
we're finding out like what is ours to
do in this sort of ecosystem and it's
like I don't want that like I don't want
I don't want to like wade into the
culture war and and like like show
people how to have conversations or
whatever like that that just does not
appeal to me personally I'm real and I'm
know that like somebody better do that
somebody better do that yeah yeah yeah
that's a really good point I feel like
that is my piece to hold is what that's
sort of memetic mediation between
different tribes or at least seeing
where where the different tribes are who
the liminal figures or figures who might
be able to reach between these sort of
warring tribes might be and then to try
and do interviews with them like that's
something I feel really drawn towards
actually that puts into perspective a
lot of the previous conversation
conversations we've had like you and I
would say Peter Lindbergh have a really
solid understanding of the landscape of
tribes that that I have no idea no clue
about and maybe you're on the same page
I don't know I don't know you know and I
think you you make a sacrifice by being
there but also getting that exposure
like I walk into London no offense to
any of Londoners there but I need to get
out immediately I cannot stay there and
you know you're immersed there so maybe
there are some downsides to it for you
is it that you haven't expressed but
you're the ability that you have to see
the full landscape of tribes I find
fascinating and Peter you know just
probably as much to do with the
journalistic background as as anything
yeah yes I was seeing where the tribes
are coming from and seeing what the
cultural landscape is and where the
pressure points might be on that
landscape I think is is kind of what I'm
interested in it could be a matter of my
ignorance but I keep when I look at the
tribes though I also think the solutions
still all the same that there's still
this hyper identification with your
tribe and and with ideas and you know if
it's not one thing it's another and if
one thought for more one kind of
identity or developmental level is
breaking down you just swing over to
another one and continue there and so
it's if part of the fuel for me not to
come into the tribal conversation
because it seems like the solution
should is just go into isolation Jordan
Peterson says clean up your room go
focus on fixing your own life and then
go out into the world and maybe don't
join any tribes just just be
with what are your thoughts on that yeah
I mean expect I feel this particularly
in terms of the American political
context that and we've I feel like I've
sort of gone in a little bit every I
feel a real sense of if I'm gonna start
sitting down and having conversations
with people who are deeply immersed and
there's so much heat and there's not
some this some heat sunlight as well but
there's a lot of heat in that
conversation and I look at these
political channels that have like a
million followers or and and it's such a
I feel like the meta conversation is a
good place to avoid that in some ways
like there's there's a little bit of
hiding there for me because I do I do
know the political landscape well enough
to be able to have those conversations
and just sort of see where it's coming
from but at the same time I find it
quite intimidating like it's scary it
honestly scares me as well because I
feel like I need to do a lot more
research so I'm gonna have these
conversations I need to be but there's a
lot more exposure there's a lot more
potential for one side or the other to
start saying and for example the just a
small example like that the interview I
did with Dave Rubin for example was the
first interview that I did where I felt
he's obviously sort of identified with
the intellectual dark where when we've
done stuff on the inside dark web but I
as I was researching that interviewers
like I'm also a journalist and actually
I think a lot of what Dave Rubin does is
there's some serious questions that need
to be asked about whether he is fulfil
it what role he's fulfilling in the
cultural landscape how he conducts his
interviews those have really valid
questions and personally for my own
integrity I feel I need to ask him these
questions there wasn't a huge blowback
from that like we we don't have the
profile for those who've been a huge
blowback from that interview but there
was some blowback from that interview
there was some people on the comments
thread saying
you ambushed him or you were whatever
kind of like you you're you're smearing
him or whatever like a taste of that
sort of there's energy there and it's it
sort of feels like it's easy to get
pulled into wanting that kind of
response but also there's a there's a
it's a double-edged sword as well of
like being drawn into that political
conversation but I can see it being very
tempting to be part of that
twitter twitter kind of fighting and
yeah and part of my personality likes
that kind of stuff as well so it's
really does that answer your question of
this or i think so but it also brings up
an interesting thought about dave rubin
that we've been discussing actually i
think it was a discussion with you about
the need for people kind of spearheading
new knowledge for all of humanity in
people who are generalist trying to
connect the dots of all these experts
out there and and I see you and Dave
kind of occupying the same sphere except
you're not saying I'm a thought leader
of this of any specific area and Dave
Rubin saying like I'm I'm part of the
intellectual deep web he's like he's not
really he's just putting connections
together and but you're you're making an
effort not to just be seen a certain way
but also to participate in it you know
and make those connections facilitate
with conversations but you're not
claiming to be anything you're not it
doesn't seem like you're claiming to be
anything yeah I'd say that Dave Rubin
doesn't necessarily claim like he
actually did say in the interview with
me that he he feels like the connective
tissue for all of these conversations
rather than an intellectual himself so I
did want to give him give him that I
think my critique of him would be more
and I could I also had this conversation
with Joe Shapiro recently like Dave
Rubin is a cautionary tale of what can
happen on the Internet because you can
easily get into a position where you are
audience capture becomes a thing the
dynamics like this is a fascinating
thing I'd love to explore at length at
some point and but the different
dynamics between being in the mainstream
media to being on YouTube are huge and
there's danger
both but the big dangers in YouTube for
example a few days ago I put out a film
where I talked to James Lindsay and I it
was about impossible conversations I
made the point to him that he doesn't
really model that on Twitter and his
defense was the Twitter performance and
I put I played both sides of that
criticism I played a guy who was
criticizing Lindsay and then played his
response in full which I thought was a
really fair way to do it I didn't sort
of I didn't if it had been a channel 4
news piece for example I might have led
with with a slightly more sensationalist
take and cut it a little bit more but I
played the whole thing I played the
whole exchange and there were still
people in the thread saying you you
shouldn't treat a guest like that it's
like it's fascinating like the different
expectations we have of YouTube versus
mainstream media and one of the other
big ones is that if you're one I was
working for channel 4 news if you ask
come on for an interview you're doing
them a massive favor and you have this
sort of institutional authority behind
you that you can treat your guests
whatever way you want and it's expected
it's expected that you will ask them the
tough questions you don't and you're in
trouble
whereas on YouTube it's a completely
different dynamic you you have you have
a difficulty when you're starting out
like if I just attack everyone I have in
my channel quickly get to the point
where no one want to go on the channel
so you have this very different
relationship with the guests who've
agreed to come on and it's very easy to
then slip into kind of justifying a very
softball style for example which I've
seen Dave Rubin do and I also don't
think that that in itself is a problem
you have to in a way to understand what
Dave Rubin is up to you it's a very deep
question
there's a set of films by a guy called
timber on toast where and it takes in
four hours to go through what the
problems are with a Rubin show and it's
mainly that he doesn't it only goes one
way there's a narrative that Davis has
about the left and all of his guests fit
that narrative and he doesn't push back
against part of that narrative that
don't fit and so he's what he's doing is
a very partial rendering of a
complex cultural landscape and for
another perspective collapsing what
needs to be a very high-resolution
critique of say the left or the culture
into a very low resolution critique and
when he has other people on his podcast
who don't fit that and actually have
some fairly reprehensible views who if
they were on the left he would
definitely ask them about definitely
criticize he doesn't criticize them so
it's like it's a really fascinating like
that dynamic of the different
expectations of mainstream versus
YouTube media and and how that can lead
to corruption of the truth on both sides
because I think on the mainstream side
you just get caught in sensationalism
you just get caught in a sort of pseudo
oppositional but you saw that with the
Kathy Newman Jordan Peterson interviewer
but that whole modality just collapsed
because Jordan Pederson was because of
Jordan Peterson wasn't who Kathy Neiman
was it's just like hang on this is this
whole thing just look weird what's
interesting about this whole meta
conversation and the event that we're at
right now is is the analyzing the meta
conversation and the places that people
are coming from in these conversations
like what is the intention what is the
thing I'm trying to do when I'm
interviewing someone or having a
conversation I like the way Jordan
Peterson approaches it because he's just
trying to find truth he's trying to
uncover dig up truth and people keep
approaching him from these lenses of
like what's your agenda or try and drag
him in the political sphere and so like
there's this whole new conversation
that's arising that is is addressing
that meta intention behind interviewers
and and people engaged in a conversation
that I'm really fascinated by and and
the three of us are actually all
approaching it in completely different
ways too which is like you know I'm in a
conversation with my wife that other
people sometimes join and it's just I
don't give a what other people say
I don't give a what the
conversation is I don't care if it's
popular or not I just want to go there
and and I suffer for that in other ways
and you said you're having like a dance
with the the person the person you're
interviewing and it's really one-on-one
so there is more of like that dance you
know and you've got like this
journalistic perspective and you're
trying to you
you're seeing it through that lens and
trying to ask hard-hitting questions and
do your job as a journalist so yeah I
really find the the flavor that it takes
the conversation in to be really
different which is why we can all occupy
the same sense making whatever you want
to call it intellectual deep web space
but have such different flavors and the
exact same conversations you know one
thing that came up for me too is like
there is a way I think in which the
solution is the same for all of these
different mimetic tribes right yeah it
is this like humiliation and recognition
that my vision and understanding of the
world isn't what is actually going to
get us there right and like so there is
that kind of unit a unitary solution and
there's this like hyper sophistication
needed to interface with the current
like reality of how narratives get
constructed constructed and how the
culture gets constantly reconstituted
and and constructed right and like that
you can see that and that you can do
that like I can't do that I can't see
all those things that you see because of
your training enables you to see that
and but you also have the vision of this
kind of like post identity possible
future that I think will uniquely afford
you to interface with different tribal
systems in a way that doesn't then isn't
simply trying to convert them to your
tribal system but it's trying to invite
them somewhere else that we can then
kind of be having those countries I mean
you have those conversations too but
there's less like gotcha or like trying
to catch people in our world because
we're kind of like playing the same game
in a way that I think it's important
that we do that but also we need to call
out people who like are playing other
games in ways that aren't helping yeah
yeah yeah and there's a even just the
terminology like gotcha and for example
the the interview with Dave Rubin which
I'm I'm actually very I don't enjoy
cognitive interviews or all that kind of
asking the difficult questions but
there's been occasion where I've felt
that I've had to do that because
I'm like I can't have an interview with
this person without doing that like the
John Cleese interview being a classic
example where a few days before he had
this huge media storm over comments he
made about London I was like oh no this
interview had been in the works for like
six months and it's night on now now I'm
gonna have to ask John Cleese whether
what he meant by those tweets and a lot
of people in the press calling him a
racist and some of that I don't want to
want to ask John Cleese whether he
whether is tweet or racist I I don't
want to this is one of my kind of comedy
heroes who is doing us a massive favor
by by agreeing to the interview and it's
like I don't want to have to do that but
I also feel that I can't not ask the
question and and that maybe might sort
of just just a sign of a relic of my
journalistic background but I also feel
I feel the weight of could know what
John Cleese didn't give any interviews
about this and pretty much everyone in
the media would have wanted into John
Cleese oh it's a big it's a big
journalistic event or get to have him on
the channel at all and I also know that
all of my former colleagues would if
they notice that that's going on at all
would be like I can't you call yourself
a journalist you had an interview with
John Cleese and you didn't ask him about
the biggest news event he's had over the
last three years so there is that kind
of going on as well and I'm starting to
second-guess myself whether I'm just
doing it because of that rather than
like what is what what is required but I
felt like I know I have to ask him this
and actually he was fine he was fine to
reply to that question and I think I
think the integrity for me that what the
space that I think we've carved out with
rebel wisdom is in the in the free
speech free speech space so I think
there is an injunction to ask those kind
of questions but yeah you can hear the
kind of the triple and quadruple
guessing that goes on yeah you know I
like what you said that there's like
you're almost attracted to this space
because there's a lot of heat right like
that's actually kind of calling you and
what came to me was that within the
alchemical tradition right heat is a
necessary part of the transmutation
process right if you can actually learn
to enter into that
that heat and use it to kind of create a
transformative process like that's huge
that's really significant and so I kind
of actually had the flip where I was
like oh this you're right this isn't
gotcha this is actually like something
else is perhaps happening here it's
really interesting yeah yeah the gotcha
term was was because there were some
people who referred to the Dave Rubin
interview as a gotcha interview I firmly
disagree with with that I mean I I
didn't like I said I don't enjoy those
and I didn't actually watch the Dave
Rubin interview back for quite a while
afterwards cuz I felt and then when I
watched it back I was like actually
that's a really good I was really happy
with how it went and I still think it's
one of the better interviews that I've
done because I made very clear with the
questions that came earlier on why I was
leading up to what I was leading up to
like what is the IDW is it about
difficult conversations is it about and
framing it within a context where I
thought it led on very naturally to
saying well how about this and how about
this but it's I find it yeah I don't I
don't enjoy that I don't find it but but
I feel you must yes yeah yeah related to
this whole subject of of how to have a
conversation how to debate I I think
there's this meta thing happening with
this whole intellectual deep web
movement or whatever you want to call it
that is like weird or at least some of
us out there are trying to have
conversations and demonstrate how to
increase sense-making and come to truth
together through debate sometimes
through those difficult hot moments with
other people and I think that's really
contributing and whether people are
conscious of it or not to the popularity
of this the explosion of this whole
movement because we've lost the ability
to actually have sense making debates
and conversations as a society and to
watch these different dynamics you know
arguments and debates actually come to
an end point where we all have learned
something instead of just a
dick-measuring contest it's like it's a
really to me it's a new phenomenon
it's fascinating and I think other
people are tuning in for that reason and
we're it's also like they're they're
learning from it and applying it in
their own lives too yeah yeah we're
probably hitting the one and a half hour
mark and the conversation I think we
should definitely do it again of really
yeah a lot of really fascinating
emergent perspectives here is there
anything that we feel that we want to
and take the opportunity of the last
sort of five or ten minutes to know this
is that this is really pleasurable for
me I think part of what made it so
enjoyable was that we like spent time
together leading up to this and there's
a feeling of like safety and
togetherness that yeah I think allowed
this conversation to to emerge the way
it did and so on yeah it's beautiful
yeah I agree yeah
I'm also look I'm always looking for
that that kind of what value can be
extracted which is actually part of my
lens as well it's like what is the
actionable thing at the end of this
because is the rational person trying to
deconstruct rationality it's like what's
my homework what's the thing I take from
this so I'm interested to know your
guys's perspectives on this conversation
from that standpoint what is at least
what is emerging or where do you think
this is going this conversation is going
and what is actionable for people are
useful out of what we talked about or
just personally what has been useful for
you yeah in terms of where the
conversation is going I think very much
does felt certainly we felt this sense
of reaching some kind of synthesis of
the intellectually embodied and the need
for in-person
meetups and events to take this work
forward so we're putting on what we call
in the collective intelligence lab we
were just practicing with some of these
technologies some of these practices and
coming together to see if we can create
something that's more than the sum of
its parts and orient it towards the
cultural moment whatever the cultural
moment is whether they're having
difficult conversations or whether
that's thinking about existential risk
or whether that what whatever the topics
are certainly the the collective
intelligence collective sense making is
another good word collective wisdom is
something I really like as well what
does that look like and this also this
sense of different people from all of
these different places for example I'm
struck by John bhave key for example I
think he's got he's got such an amazing
perspective and also what's been really
wonderful to see is he since he put out
solar putting out his series awakening
from the meaning crisis he has become
swept up in this evolving conversation
and he's met so many interesting people
Ian's for having all of these
fascinating conversations and this sense
of a community self-organizing around
these bigger questions is really
interesting and really fruitful so I'm
also interested in who are the people
that should be in dialogue with each
other to move these conversations
forward the the this sort of ambassadors
from the different mimetic tribes for a
is one way of looking at it that's an
interesting place it's like what at what
are the what are the people and
conversations that need to be had to
move things forward and then what is the
relationship between in person
collective intelligence practice that's
that's where I feel the conversation has
reached now in the last two years I
think that I think we had a sort of
trajectory of the Trump brexit moment of
well okay something for me it was like
okay this is the time oh this is the
time when this is gonna when all of
these things are going to be needed when
like for me it's the death it's the
death rattle of the the old way like
Trump is if we talk about game a and
game B Trump is game a and Connacht it's
like he operates in a zero he is game
theory incarnate he ought to operate in
a zero trust world
he creates chaos he he is it's it's it's
basically game theory prisoner's dilemma
where if you trust someone you're a
moron because someone will will you
over down the line
Trump is that Trump is that and he so
him like that for me is like he is the
apotheosis of game a so game be this
this has to be the time like over the
next however many years has to be the
time to this game B Network to solidify
and hopefully show itself to be superior
at out competing game a so it sort of
growing in the cracks of game a then
there's all of these other questions
about how do you then kind of guard
against people who are using co-opting
it or using game B terminology without
actually being game B all of that sort
of stuff and knowing that unless we've
dealt with our own stuff and desire to
as Jamie wheel says like snatch the ring
like you've got to be being aware of
like that's where the conversation is
going as well and kind of thinking as
I'm talking now that's a big part of
where the conversation needs to go next
especially in these game be networked
place it's like okay how do we guard
against what's an immune response for
people who are talking the talk we're
not walking the walk who are using it
for their own narcissistic ends what how
do we guard against this nascent network
being co-opted infiltrated all of these
questions are really alive for me at the
moment there's something else that's
been happening recently have really been
paying attention to which is I didn't
think of it before but people really do
try to give up their sovereigns
sometimes they really try to have
someone else make sense of the world for
them and take action in the world and it
it's is really surprised me how in even
these communities and and in the middle
of these conversations we're still
looking for that we're talk we're
literally talking about sense making and
demonstrating collective sense making
and yet people may still want to vote
you in into some position of power or me
or you you know instead of recognizing
what's happening in this conversation
which is we're trying to show others how
to do it as well what is collective
sense making let's all engage in it and
it's just I just had this vision in my
head before that dictators were
constantly the types that were co-opting
and taking power from themselves without
realizing how much people are just
handing them the power and that's
something I think is is not being
addressed enough in this conversation
that I would like to see more of yeah
yeah for my part I also see a kind of
transition point in the conversation and
I think it cores it a lot let's think
with what you're seeing like the shift
to kind of more participation and
collective intelligence and it does feel
like the network has become self-aware
and I I said I feel like I no longer
know what my role is in this thing
actually yeah I think we're it does
though feel like we're in a new phase
and this this event has kind of
crystallized that for me personally and
so I feel much more clear about that for
my own process yeah it feels like we've
been hinting at the future of some
future thing and then and then this kind
of awakening and self-awareness of this
movement has made me realize it's here
like we're we're waking up to it we can
actually have these conversations on
somewhat mainstream platforms and get
away with it you know
yeah cool thank you guys been really
really interesting and I hope that other
people find it interesting as well
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
calls to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews we're also
looking for talented people to help us
out with editing graphics music that
kind of thing and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talk a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talk about
so that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon